Bernice West Beyers
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Bernice West Beyers papers
1912-1987
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Beyers, Bernice West
1.7 linear feet
The papers of sculptor Bernice West Beyers measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1912-1987. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters that discuss sculpture commissions and exhibitions; scattered business and financial records; notes and writings; a sketchbook; printed material, including 3 scrapbooks of clippings; and photographs of Beyers and photograph albums of her art work.
Biographical Note
Berenice West Byers (1906-1987)worked as as sculptor in the New York and New England area. Later in life, she became a patron of the arts in Dallas, Texas.
Bernice Delemar West was born on April 26, 1906 in New York City, the daughter of Abigail Palmer and E. Lovette West, an engineer. In 1925 she graduated from the Bennett School in Millbrook, New York, where she took diplomas in both drama and fine arts. After a summer trip to Europe with classmates, she spent the next year studying drama with Winifred Lenihan at the Theatre Guild. In the summer of 1926, she did summer stock in Binghamton as a member of Actors Equity. In 1927 she began to pursue a career in sculpture and pottery.
She first worked in the studio of Lu Duble, her former teacher at the Bennett School. From 1927 to 1929, she also studied under Alexander Archipenko, Edmond R. Amateis, and Winold Reiss. In the fall of 1929, West began studies at the Art Students League under William Zorach.
Beginning in 1934, she exhibited primarily in New England and Florida. She was later influenced by the Haitian and Mayan art work she encountered while on a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1937-1938.
West was married in March 1940 to Robert Arthur Beyers, and their family moved permanently to Dallas, Texas, where they were primarily patrons of the arts.
Bernice West Beyers died in 1987.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor Bernice West Beyers measure 1.7 linear feet and date from 1912-1987. Found within the papers are biographical material; letters that discuss sculpture commissions and exhibitions; scattered business and financial records; notes and writings; a sketchbook; printed material, including 3 scrapbooks of clippings; and photographs of Beyers and photograph albums of her art work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series. All series are arranged chronologically. All oversized material has been housed in Box 3 (sol) and is referenced in the folder headings of the Series Description/Container Listing.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1923-1935, undated (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1928-1974, undated (Box 1; 16 folders)
Series 3: Business Records, 1923-1960, undated (Box 1; 11 folders)
Series 4: Notes and Writings, 1925-1967, undated (Box 1, 3; 10 folders)
Series 5: Art Work, undated (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1912-1987, undated (Box 1, 3; 33 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1937-1956, undated (Box 1, 2, 3; 29 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms.
Subjects-Topical:
Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century; Women sculptors -- New York (State); Sculptors -- New York (State)
Types of Materials:
Works of art; Sketchbooks; Photographs
Provenance
The Bernice West Beyers papers were donated in 1988 by Robert West Beyers, the artist's son.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1923-1935, undated, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Biographical material consists of report cards from the Bennett School of Liberal and Applied Arts, membership certificates including an Actors' Equity card, and an award certificate.
  - Report Cards, 1923-1924 (Box 1)
  - Membership Certificates and Award Certificate, 1926-1935, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1928-1974, undated, Series 2:; (Box 1; 16 folders)
  Correspondence consists of letters exchanged between Beyers, members of her family, and colleagues. Many letters discuss commissions and exhibitions of her sculpture. There is one letter, 1951, signed by Alexander Archipenko.
  - Correspondence, 1928-1974, undated, (16 folders) (Box 1)
- Business Records, 1923-1960, undated, Series 3:; (Box 1; 11 folders)
  Business records primarily consist of miscellaneous receipts, price lists, and patent records relating to Beyers' designs for an ashtray and for an automobile hood ornament.
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1923-1960, undated, (9 folders) (Box 1)
  - Patent Records, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Price Lists, 1933, undated (Box 1)
- Notes and Writings, 1925-1967, undated, Series 4:; (Box 1, 3; 10 folders)
  Notes include a notebook listing information about miscellaneous art work, transcripts of radio interviews, and miscellaneous notes. Writings consist of miscellaneous typescripts written by Beyers.
  - Notebook Concerning Art Work, 1931-1939 (Box 1)
  - Transcript of Radio Interviews, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Notes on Etching, undated (Box 1)
  - Caption Cards for Art Work, 1967, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1925-1933, undated, (See Also Box 3) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Typescripts, 1933-1941, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Oversized Blueprint of Portrait Plaque of Fred H. Albee, 1925 (Box 3 (sol))
  - Oversized Blueprint of a Wooden Easel, 1933 (Box 3 (sol))
- Art Work, undated, Series 5:; (Box 1; 2 folders)
  Art work consists of a sketchbook containing geometric designs, and an abstract pencil drawing.
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box 1)
  - Drawing, undated (Box 1)
- Printed Material, 1912-1987, undated, Series 6:; (Box 1, 3; 33 folders)
  Printed material consists of clippings, scrapbooks of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, programs primarily from Beyers' plays and readings, brochures including one from the General Bronze Corporation, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Clippings, 1912-1966, undated, (12 folders; See Also Box 3) (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1921-1927, (6 folders; See Box 3 for Scrapbook 2) (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1933-1987, undated, (7 folders) (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1917-1926, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1932, undated (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of Art Work by Others, undated (Box 1)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 1)
  - Oversized Clippings, 1931 (Box 3 (sol))
  - Scrapbook 2, 1934-1946 (Box 3 (sol))
- Photographs, 1937-1956, undated, Series 7:; (Box 1-3; 29 folders)
  This series consists primarily of photographs of art works, both unbound and in albums. There are also photographs of Beyers and her exhibitions.
  - Photographs of Bernice West Beyers, 1937, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Art Exhibitions, 1941,undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph Album 1, undated, (See Also Box 3; 4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photograph Album 2, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Photograph Album 3, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (hol))
  - Photograph Album 4, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (hol))
  - Photograph Album 5, undated (Box 2 (hol))
  - Photographs of Art Work by Beyers, 1956, undated, (13 folders) (Box 2 (hol))
  - Photographs of Art Work by others, undated (Box 2 (hol))
  - Oversized Cover for Photograph Album 1, undated (Box 3 (sol))